<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A glympse of that jevvel, judicial, just, preserving libertie. By Jo. Streater, a member of the Army of the Commonwealth of England serving in Ireland.</title>
            <author>Streater, John, fl. 1650-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E690_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863540</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863540</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 106:E690[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A glympse of that jevvel, judicial, just, preserving libertie. By Jo. Streater, a member of the Army of the Commonwealth of England serving in Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Streater, John, fl. 1650-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the black Spread-Eagle at the West end of Paul's.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GLYMPSE OF THAT JEWEL, <hi>Judicial, Juſt, Preſerving</hi> LIBERTIE. <hi>By</hi> JO. STREATER, <hi>a Member of the Army of the Commonwealth of</hi> England <hi>ſerving in</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt end of PAUL'S. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166475:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166475:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the general temper of People, to ſlight the look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after matters of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick concernment, they conceiving, that they are mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters too high for common capacities, and more becoming Stateſ-men. That that I ſhall urge, is, that every Member of the Common-wealth, of right and in duty, ought to watch to their Liberty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Abſoluteneſs in perſons of great Truſt. True, thou art to be obedient to Higher Powers, but that command or exhortation obligeth thee no farther then the Higher Powers act for the general good.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that the Higher Powers ſhould command thee to ſlay thy fellow Member of the Commonwealth, wouldſt thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them therein? but if they command
<pb facs="tcp:166475:3"/>thee to preſerve and defend thy fellow Member, his Liberty, Life, Eſtate, thou art in purſuance thereof bound to hazard thine; That that thou obeyeſt them in, thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be able to judg whether he doth right therein or not.</p>
            <p>Be not miſtaken in higher Powers, they ought to be bound up by a law of mutuall conſent of the Generality. <hi>Alexander</hi> grew a cruel Tyrant after his flatterers told him he was a God. 'Tis the onely way to give the advantage into the hands of thoſe thou chuſeſt to execute thy Laws of conſent, to make themſelves Maſters of the common Liberty, to ſet too high an eſtimation on them, or think it is theirs of right: Yet the Authoritie that ſhould preſerve equity between man and man, ſhould not bee ſlighted, for by that means Authority will be weakned.</p>
            <p>Make good thy claim to Equity, and to thy right in election of perſons in truſt; Indeavour to underſtand thy Liberty; ſince Monarchy is deſtroyed, thou haſt a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect equalitie, in reſpect of thy Rights and Priviledges. Fear not any, be they never
<pb facs="tcp:166475:3"/>ſo powerfull, if thou haſt Equitie on thy ſide. Do not ſeek and ſcrape for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, nor make parties to obtain thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; thou knoweſt not what thou doeſt; therein thou betrayeſt thy Self, thy Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and thy Countrie. Do not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prejudicate. If thou ſueſt for Right, let thy Judges ſtand in fear of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee wrong. Is Equitie and Juſtice theirs to give? No, it is their dutie; it is not their dutie to tire thee with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes. Endeavour to know the Power of thy Judges, thy right, the Lawes; ſo that though it be not fit or ſafe for thee to be a Judg in thy own Cauſe; yet that thou mayeſt judg him that judgeth thee. And to the end that thou mayeſt know the poſition of Affaires, converſe often with knowing men: and let knowing men endeavour to inform the leſſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lycurgus</hi> accounted this an eminent prop or pillar to the State of <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> that his Citizens ſhould converſe and confer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of their Liberties, of Government, of Laws, of Peace, of War; and every one to
<pb facs="tcp:166475:4"/>be as able to rule, as thoſe that are choſen to rule: It is hard to rob ſuch a people of their Liberties. Likewiſe, one Rule would be wel to be obſerved, That if places of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were made leſſe profitable, they would be leſſe deſired: when it muſt be undergone for conſcience ſake, eſteem of none but ſuch as are truly virtuous. Thoſe that endeavour to enrich themſelves, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or kindred, are not perſons fit for truſt. It is thy duty to watch to thy Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo it is alſo thy duty to watch to the Execution of the Lawes that are for thy Preſervation. It is not onely thy duty to watch to thy owne Liberty, but to thy neighbours Libertie; nay thy poor neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Libertie, that the rich and mighty oppreſſe him not. <hi>Hercules</hi> was deified for imploying his ſtrength in delivering the oppreſſed out of the hands of the oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>The way that the <hi>Nimrods</hi> of this world grow mighty and powerful by, is to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige ſuch as may be hurtfull to them, ſo that they may diſ-ingage them from joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the generality in defence of their Libertie; ſo that the Generalitie having
<pb facs="tcp:166475:4"/>their Captains taken away, become a prey to their Abſoluteneſſe; as <hi>AEſop's</hi> ſheep ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their dogs delivered to the Wolves, became at length a prey unto the Wolves.</p>
            <p>Flatter none of thy fellow-members of the Commonwealth with Titles, as, <hi>High and Mighty,</hi> or <hi>Excellent;</hi> The Title of <hi>Honor,</hi> or <hi>Honorable,</hi> is the higheſt mark of deſert that a Member of a Commonwealth is fit to attain unto or bear.</p>
            <p>Reader, Here thou art guided to know thy ſelf, to know others; Their Power and thy Liberty. There is no one thing under Heaven the cauſe of miſery by the aſſumed Lording of Uſurpers, but <hi>Thy not knowing thy Liberties and Rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Confuſedly have I preſented thee with a Glympſe of that, which I doubt not, if thou wilt caſt thine eye to behold, thou wilt diſcover a greater light herein, then is diſcerned by him that is a wel-wiſher to</hi> Publick Preſerving Libertie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J.S</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:166475:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166475:5"/>
            <head>A glimpſe of that Jewel; Judicial, juſt preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Libertie.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as Monarchie is deſtroyed amongſt us, it is convenient, and much in order to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the juſt rights of every member of the Common-wealth, that they ſhould underſtand their Rights, Priviledges and Liberties. It was obſervable, that when <hi>Rome</hi> grew to that greatneſſe, that by its Vertues and Arms it not onely preſerved it ſelf, but gave Lawes to other Cities, Common-wealths and Princes, it was when every member of that Common-wealth perfectly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the myſteries of State, and were competent Judges in all matters and cauſes ariſing in the Common-wealth, as alſo of the diſadvantage or advantage of either Peace or Warr.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The great preſervation and cauſe of the growth of the Common-wealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> after their ſhaking off that yoak, Monarchie, was the yearly election of all Officers in greateſt truſt, both Military and Civil; for by this means they were prevented of obtaining to thoſe advantages of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelves Maſters of the common Liberty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By this means alſo every one of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth that affected Government, had hope of having ſhare of the Government; therefore they endeavoured to improve themſelves ſo, as to become capable of ſuch and ſuch truſts in Government: So that almoſt every one was an able defendant of their Libertie and Countrie: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the greatneſſe of that Empire is not to be admired; for it is hard to oppoſe ſuch a compoſed Bodie, by ſuch a Body or power as is acted or ſupported by the Counſels or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts of few. <hi>Romes</hi> power began to decline, when the power and ſecret reaſons of State were aſſumed by few, or one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. They never received ſuch a ſtroak at their Libertie, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166475:6"/>when <hi>Caeſar</hi> was made perpetual Dictator: Therefore ſince we finde <hi>Rome</hi> ſtrip'd of her liberty and glory, let <hi>England</hi> watch to hers: and to that end let us take notice of the wayes how perſons that affect abſolute Government endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the accompliſhment thereof; the which may be found by knowing what ſhould be on the contrary to preſerve it from that danger.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Government ſhould or ought to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of mankinde: for as government and Law is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a rational reſtraint of abſolute Libertie; ſo it is alſo a rational reſtraint of abſoluteneſſe in command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And natural equity teacheth us, 1. That no one ſhould deſire profit or honour by the prejudicing of another. 2. That no one ſhould do or wiſh that to another, which he would not ſhould be done unto himſelf. Now ſeeing in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that every perſons intereſt and good in that bodie is concerned, 'tis cleer that the power is eſſentially in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But foraſmuch as the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> is ſo large, that it cannot meet as <hi>Rome, Athens, Sparta,</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> in a Market place, or in a Theater, in Councel, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or matters of State; therefore it hath been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> for many hundred years, to contract their Authority in a Repreſentative or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: Indeed, their Kings never had any other power, then as their chiefeſt Miniſter of State and was no other then a member of the Common-wealth, bound up by the ſame Law and Rules of government; witneſs the Oath of Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as alſo the Oath adminiſtred to all Juſtices, both of the peace, and the ſeveral Benches, <hi>An.</hi> 18, <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>St.</hi> 3. in theſe words, <hi>You ſhall ſwear well and truly to ſerve your Lord the King, and the People.</hi> Likewiſe the King often appeared by his Atturney at the Bar of the Common-wealth, ſometimes as Plaintiff, ſometimes as Defendant, in ſeveral caſes at Law; nay, when the late King was at the height of his Supremacy, <hi>Hambden</hi> and <hi>Chambers</hi> brought their Action againſt him at common Law, in the caſe of Ship-money; they knowing that the power to impoſe Laws and Taxes, conſiſted in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people repreſented in Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166475:6"/>
            <p>It was notably obſerved by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> of <hi>Solon;</hi> being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen chief in Government of the Common-wealth of <hi>Athens,</hi> the people being aſſembled in the Market place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he coming to ſit in Councel with them, when he drew nigh the Aſſembly of the people, he cauſed the Rod that was born before him (which was a mark or enſigne of Government) the head to be turned downward, to ſignifie, that eſſentially the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was in the People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore ſeeing that Power and Government is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially the right of the People, for the good of the generality, or the greateſt number, it is to be preſumed, it muſt be in oppoſition to ſome, namely the vicious and fooliſh; <hi>A rod for the fools back,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes. <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That true Government is when men govern by Vertue and Wiſdome; which is in oppoſition to vice and folly, as afore mentioned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To prevent the having the Power wreſted out of the hands of the People by an aſſumed abſoluteneſſe of perſons in truſt; Suffer not great power to continue longer then one year in the hands of any one member of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Doubtleſs, it was upon the ſame reaſon of State that that Act of Parliament was paſs'd <hi>An.</hi> 4. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was ordained, that Parliaments ſhould be choſen once a yeer, or oftner, if need be. One reaſon why it is not for the good of the Publick for long continuance of perſons in truſt, is becauſe that continuance in any one action or undertaking whatſoever, burdeneth the ſpirits; for the ſpirits that give life to all action, moſt uſually ſpend vigorouſly upon novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but being ſpent, are no other then as tired jades, that leave one half of their work undone. A ſecond reaſon why a prefixt time for the continuance of perſons in Publick truſts (as one year, not more, rather leſs) would be much to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the publick, is, when they ſee one year is the time of their continuance, they wil be deſirous to do ſomething in that time worthie of themſelves, to preſerve their memory, and to obtain a good opinion of the Publick; they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it unworthy of themſelves to leave any thing undone that ſhould be for the good of the Publick, or that they ſhould not relieve diſtreſſed perſons that have made their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166475:7"/>applications to them for redreſſe: by this means Petitions wil not lie dormant three, four, or five years. Thirdly, It will oblige them to do that which ſhall indeed be for the good of the Publick, they knowing, that at the determination of the prefixt time of their Truſt, they ate in no other conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then the reſt of the members of the Common-wealth, and ſo ſhall have an equal benefit of thoſe good Laws and Proviſions of publick ſafety which they have been inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in for publick good. It will not be ſafe in new Elections to chuſe any that have ſerved in a Repreſentative again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till five yeers be expired or more.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In your choice have regard to this rule, to chuſe men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſs; for undeniably co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs is the in-let to all manner of corruption, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in-juſtice and Tyranny: Covetouſneſs in a perſon of great truſt, is evil in theſe two reſpects: either firſt, he is covetous from a baſe worldly mind, and therefore unfit for Government; or ſecondly, being deſirous of greatneſs, is covetous to obtain wherewith to ſupport his greatneſs, or defend him in his greatneſs; and therefore in a Common-wealth dangerous.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The manner of the choice of Members repreſentative in a Parliament, ſhould be ſo, as to prevent making of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for the party, or number of men that prevaileth in their Election of any one, obligeth him that is elected; and on the contrary, thoſe that oppoſe that Election, him that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected will conceive himſelf diſobliged to them: therefore to prevent thoſe incoveniencies. A more equality of choice will be ſafe (as when for Knights of the Shire, and Burgeſſes, there are to be two pitch'd upon by the conſent of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Burrough) that the County or Burrough ſhould chuſe ten wiſe and honeſt men, and out of them ten, elect two by lot; by this means, making of parties will be prevented, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many will be prompt to improve their parts, ſo as they may be fit for ſo great a truſt; likewiſe it will oblige more to the owning of that Government, wherein they ſee s poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of having ſhare of.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the perſons chuſing, as well as thoſe choſen or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166475:7"/>elected, ſhould not be perſons diſaffected to the publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That no one member of the Commonwealth have too much power committed into his hands, leſt he make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Lord of the common Liberty, or at leaſt become thereby too powerful to be dealt with; to call ſuch perſons to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count may prove dangerous, for they to ſecure themſelves, uſually make uſe of their power in defending themſelves, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> when he made himſelf Lord of the Empire. <hi>Alcibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades</hi> (being told <hi>Pericles</hi> was making up his accounts to the Commonwealth) ſaid, That he rather ſhould ſtudy that he might not give the Commonwealth an account, the which <hi>Pericles</hi> had done, had not the Commonwealth of <hi>Athens</hi> watched him the better.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the Lawes of the Commonwealth ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and abbreviated, fit for the underſtanding of every one of capacity. <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> when he received the power of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, he, to oblige the people, cauſed the Lawes to be written in braſs; for if people underſtand their Liberty and Lawes, they are not ſo ſubject to be oppreſſed; and therefore 'tis the policy of him that would invade the liberty of a people, to keep them ignorant.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Thoſe in power ſhould be ſparing of the publick Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, for oft times they diſpoſe of it in favour to oblige ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whereby to ſtrengthen their intereſt; which is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; for that which is given by a Commonwealth, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, it muſt be real, for they have not that advantage, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow empty titles of honour, as Princes have (when their coffers arc empty) to ſatisfie the ambitious or covetous.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That if a Commonwealth be neceſſitated to keep arms to juſtifie their intereſt, it will be ſafe that Diſcipline be ſtrictly obſerved. otherwiſe they will become inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and therefore in the Summer, their Forces ſhould rather be encamped in the field: by this means Diſcipline would be preſerved, Factions prevented, they would not be faſtned to thoſe relations, they would be more entire in bodies, conſequently more ready to anſwer the neceſſities of the publick, in caſe of invaſion or inſurrection. It was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166475:8"/>obſervable, the <hi>Romans</hi> were more ſtrict of Diſcipline in peace then in time of War.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That no priviledges be taken away from any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations or Societies (provided that every member of theſe Corporations or Societies have an equal benefit in thoſe priviledges) but rather new granted: by this means <hi>Philip</hi> the wiſe made ſure his eſtate: The Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> did the like. Lawes, Priviledges and Cuſtomes, and the like, have been the only Pales and Defences againſt Tyranny and Abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; they have been as meers between common right and abſoluteneſs; and thoſe that attempt the taking away of theſe Defences, may be juſtly ſuſpected of making prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to abſoluteneſs.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That no member of the Commonwealth ought to have guards for his perſon. <hi>Numa Pomphilia</hi> being choſen King, he told his Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> (upon the diſcharging of the 300 men at armes) that foraſmuch as he was intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Government by them, it was as reaſonable for him to truſt them with his perſon. So <hi>Timolian</hi> being by the Commonwealth of <hi>Corinth</hi> ſent to aid <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> being Victor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and having obtained the Caſtle of <hi>Dionyſins,</hi> cauſed it to be demoliſhed, and rather choſe to oblige the <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſians</hi> by Juſtice and Liberty, then to faſten obedience to them by arms.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That it may be made Criminal for any perſon in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick truſt to receive any Bribes, Fees, or Gifts, that ſhall have Cauſes or Petitions depending before them; for by this means creepeth in all manner of corruption, injuſtice, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality; by which means alſo the judgment is over-ruled and corrupted. It was to prevent the like inconveniencies in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of publick Juſtice, that that Statute was enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Ann.</hi> 18. <hi>of Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>You ſhall not ſuffer your ſelf, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for you, to take gift of Gold or Silver, or any other thing, that may turn to your profit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. It will be of great advantage to appoint twelve Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of State, that ſhould be qualified with abilities and judgment in Moral, Civil, and Common Law, as alſo the Law of Nations, and Military policy, the intereſt of forreign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166475:8"/>and States, that at all times the Supreme Authority may demand their advice in caſes of difficulty: but it is not fit they ſhould be imployed in any thing but in advice; it is not fit nor ſafe, they ſhould be qualified with the leaſt power, not ſo much as to ſummon any perſon before them, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide or put in execution any matter Political or Judicial; it is fit they ſhould continue in this truſt, that they may be the better acquainted with matters of State, and conſtitutions of Government.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That Judges doing Juſtice in the name of the people, ſhould be honoured with robes of Honour, which upon the arraying of them, it ſhould de done in the name of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and that they continue no longer wearing thoſe Robes, then ſitting in the Judgment Seat doing Juſtice: alſo that Judges ſhould be elected once a year out of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Law.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the better to prevent confuſion, that the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Commonwealth may be preſerved in a lively and eminent manner: to that end all Courts of Juſtice ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend one upon another, and all ſhould be governed by the ſelf ſame Law: So in all matters of State, all particular Councels ſhould depend upon one Superior. As all Cities and Corporations, though by the joint conſent of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, may ordain or enact any thing for the good of that Society, yet it ſhould not be Law, until it be confirmed by the approbation of the Superior Authority, unleſs it be in ſome ſpecial caſes, wherein they have a clear right by equity in Law to do or cauſe to be put in execution, ſuch things as are for the good of that Coporation or Society, ſo that the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do not extend to any others then the members of the ſame body. Care ought to be had to unite all bodies in a Commonwealth, ſo as to depend one upon another, for the good of the whole; by this means they become powerful, and as a drop of water being united to the Ocean, becometh part of that infinite body. <hi>Tacitus</hi> telleth us that the Engliſh did conſult and make War againſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> apart, by Cities, or Counties, and therefore were overcome apart: a union of bodies, ſo as to depend one upon another, and jointly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166475:9"/>to ſupport an Authoritie over the generality, there is no ſtrength like unto this: onely have care that that Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have ſufficient checks upon them, that they may be tied up to rules to act for the general good, and not be ſwayed to intereſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Every one is to underſtand he is equally intereſſed with any member in reſpect of the common Libertie, and that there is no difference but in point of Truſt: and therefore to clear this point, 'tis fit to conſider what the nature of Law and Government is in general. <hi>Plato</hi> tels us, that Law and Government is to preſerve the undigeſted and huge lump of a Multitude, and to bring all diſcord into proportion, ſo as to become an harmony. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that all rectitude hath a being, and floweth from the fountain of being; whereas obliquitie and irregularities are meer privations and non-entities. <hi>Plato</hi> alſo ſaith, that every thing that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable hath a being, but no fruit can be gathered from priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: There is no ſweetneſſe in obliquitie; and therefore Government and Law is an wholeſome mixture of that that is juſt and profitable to all. Such Lawes the Ancients ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined were chained in a golden chain to the Chair of <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> and ſure it is, that equall and impartiall Government doth derive from God himſelf, when it doth continue and conſtitute Lawes and Conſtitutions agreeable to the welfare and happineſſe of thoſe that are to be conformable to them, and that the conſent of the whole Bodie be obtained. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> ſaith, that Law and Government is a rationall Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the advancing of the Publick good: That is Law and Government that the neceſſity of the Publick ſtandeth in need of, either to preſerve it, or to make it happy. All Law and Government originally ariſeth from the Law of Nature, to preſerve all in being and propertie. The life and power is moſt eminently ſeen in rational being, as <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> hath very rehtorically enlarged himſelf in the 12 &amp; 13 Oration of his, thus; <hi>That all rationall beings have a radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and fundamentall knowledg planted in them, budding and bloſſoming in firſt Principles bringing forth fruit, ſpreading it ſelf to fair and goodly branches of Morality, under the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166475:9"/>ſhadow of which mankinde may ſit with much complacency and delight: Therefore for the governing of ſo glorious beings, 'tis fit that Government ſhould be an abſtract from the conſent, and for the good of the generality of thoſe that a Law or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is to regulute or binde.</hi> But as it hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid, ſuch as are of greateſt power, (though not of right) have laid the greateſt claim to Government, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Laws. Much like was that Sophiſme affirmed by that Sophiſter diſputing with <hi>Socrates,</hi> when he affirmed that Law was an Antipathy to Nature, and that the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent juſtice of Nature was to rule according to Power: But <hi>Socrates</hi> (after he had ſtung the ſame <hi>Callicles</hi> with a few quick interrogations) affirms, That there was no ſuch harmony as between Law and Nature, that there is nothing preſerveth Nature more then Law; but it muſt be as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> affirmeth, when it is attended with Reaſon and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Though <hi>Rome</hi> had no Politicall Laws to check the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall pride of <hi>Tarquin,</hi> yet they had a virgin-Law of Nature which beamed out of an eternall Law, which was of ſtrength and force to revenge a modeſt <hi>Lucretia,</hi> and expel ſo licentious a Prince from his Dominions. Likewiſe a late contemptible <hi>Marcionella</hi> by putting the Neopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans in minde of their Laws granted by <hi>Charles the Fifth,</hi> did ſhake the very intereſt of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in Naples, and nothing could appeaſe them, but by aſſuring them that they might be governed by ſuch Lawes as ſhould be a preſervation to them and their poſterity. This is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every Being, they uſe to fly from ſuch things as are deſtructive to their own Species, and incline to all neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly and friendly beings that comply for preſervation. All preſervative Government and Law floweth from the law of Nature, but it is to the end Morall. Now ſince it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, that there is an undeniable right in all rationall Being, and that they ſtand conſtituted with this right from the Original, which is the law of Nature, it being the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from whence all other Laws flow: and if natural, then equall; ſo that hence may be concluded, that no perſon or perſons hath right to Government, or power in giving
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166475:10"/>Lawes, but when they ſtand conſtituted by vertue of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate election, or derivatively from ſuch perſons as are to ſtand bound up by ſuch Governors, or Government, unto which they are to be conformable; and it is as clear, that there is no way to preſerve a peoples Rights and Liberties, from ſuch as would make themſelves Lords thereof, as often or annual elections; for if the people keep the right of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten elections in their hands, it will make ſuch as affect Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment deſire to be alwayes in the peoples favour; to that end, they will endeavour to oblige the people by acts of Honour and Juſtice; the people here muſt take heed they lend not ſuch perſons too much of their favour: to prevent this kind of evil, the <hi>Athenians</hi> baniſhed ſuch as had obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or did endeavour to grow too great in the peoples fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, they looking upon them as dangerous perſons.</p>
            <p n="18">18. One of the principalleſt reaſons of <hi>Romes</hi> declining in its glory, was when that perſons in greateſt truſt inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into the peoples favour, by that means enlarged their power, and conſequently became unqueſtionable. You may diſcover them treading theſe ſteps: 1. They inſinuate into favour by pretending to be publickly affected: 2 They hedge in advantages co enlarge their power. 3. They find ſome neceſſary undertaking or other, thereby to poſſeſs the publick with an opinion of a neceſſity of imploying of them, by this means daily obtaining new advantages. But the ſafeſt way for a people in this caſe, is not to heap too much favor or Honour upon any one member of the Commonwealth, but keep ſuch a mean as may not turn to the detriment of the publick, and alwayes provide means to curb their overgrown Members, leſt a ſubverſion of their Liberties enſue.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That the Publick ought to be preferred before the private: the contrary have been the overthrow of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of many flouriſhing Commonwealths; for whilſt men have been bundling up of private advantages, rather then they will run the hazard of loſing of a few inferior and baſe contentments, (which may be called quiet, and not liberty) in contending, or at leaſt, they ſeeing that ſuch with whom they muſt contend are more powerful, they diſpair; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166475:10"/>conſidering, that it is more honourable to reſcue their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the powerful: Such a ſlaviſh ſpirit in men to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelvs to be trampled upon by their fellow Members, gives encouragement to many to attempt the making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abſolute: therefore a people that will keep their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from being infringed, muſt not fear to oppoſe the moſt powerful: 'Tis not to be underſtood an oppoſition by arms, but a legal oppoſition; but if all lawful means fail, arms may be made uſe of.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That neither Princes nor Parliaments are, or ought to be abſolute in their power; neither the one nor the other, ought to act any thing that ſhould be inconſiſtent with, or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the common good of all men. That the people of <hi>England</hi> had an undeniable right to contend againſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs in caſe of injuſtice or detriment, appeareth by the ſecond of <hi>Henry the IV. Ch.</hi> 22. wherein 'twas enacted, That no perſon ſhould be grieved for ſuing to break or alter any thing, although in Parliament enacted: So that it doth not only appear to be the right of every Member of the Commonwealth, but alſo their duty, to oppoſe all abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or illegal power that ſhal be aſſumed by any that ſhal get the ſtart of them in Authority or Greatneſs. But on the contrary, thoſe that ſhall conſpire to break, or alter the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Government, are no other then Traitors to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That all perſons upon the reſigning his or their Office, be required to give a publick account; for in private accounts there may be connivance.</p>
            <p n="22">22. When Magiſtrates do not anſwer the end repoſed in them, providing for publick peace and Juſtice: a people in this caſe may conſtitute a Power to queſtion them for their actings: provided alſo, that they ſtill have regard to keep life and ſtrengthen their Authority in ſuch perſons as ſhall act to that end that their truſt was repoſed in them for.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That a people ſtand not, by the Law of God, or the Law of Nature, bound to obey a Magiſtracy in any thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166475:11"/>that ſhall be deſtructive to the general good, or that ſhall be unjuſt to a particular; but it is the duty of every one, ſo prejudiced, to oppoſe it and declare againſt it, in teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that a people do not ſtand bound to obey or ſubmit to any thing that ſhall be deſtructive to the general, or unjuſt prejudice to a particular; as may appear, <hi>Anno</hi> 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 8. expreſly in theſe words; <hi>That it ſhall not be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Great Seal or little Seal, to diſturb or delay common right; although ſuch commands do come, the Juſtices ſhal not therefore ceaſe to do right in any point.</hi> Likewiſe, <hi>Ann.</hi> 20. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. 'Tis commanded, <hi>That all Juſtices ſhall do right to all people, not having regard to either rich or poor, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let or hindred by any commandment which may come to them from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, or from any other, or by any other cauſe: and if any ſuch do come, either Letter or Writs, the Juſtices ſhal proceed according to Law and Right notwithſtanding, as is the uſage of the Realm.</hi> So that it is clear, that none ſtand bound to ſubmit to a Magiſtracy or Authority, but wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the good of the Publick is concerned: ſo alſo it may be from hence concluded, that ſubordinate Officers ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavour the knowing their duty in relation to the publick good, then to conform themſelves to the will of their Superiours: for him that obeyeth, ſhould be able to judg whether that which is commanded be in the power of him that commandeth, elſe he that obeyeth may execute (in ſtead of the Law of the Common-wealth) the abſolute will of his Superior, which error reduceth him to ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <p n="24">24. The judgments of the people are not ſo ſubject to be corrupted as great perſons, for the people have no other end in what they deſire, but common equity; whereas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe great perſons are ſwayed by ſeveral ends and intereſts; and therefore often elections are more ſafe: for by this means the people keep the power in their own hands. Election is to be underſtood a qualifying of thoſe which are to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected with Authority to execute Law, that is extracted by mutual conſent of the generality for their good.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:166475:11"/>
            <p n="25">25. That all actions in favour of parties be laid aſide: this will be a means to keep all at an even poyze, ſo that one ſide ſhould not out-weigh in power, riches or honour; this is, for the preſervation of the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> duly obſerved at this day, as may appear by the cuſtome of the Senators to put off in Saint <hi>Marks</hi> Church, all affection, malice and quarrels, ſo that when they deliver their opinions in Senate, it is clearly for the good of the publick, without having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of private intereſt. There is an inſcription in Marble, in letters of Gold, at the entring in of the Councel Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Reinſburgh, Whoſoever thou be, Councellour or other, that in regard of thy Office goeſt into the Councel Chamber, out off, and leave before this door, all private affections, anger, violence, hatred, friendſhip or flattery; ſubmit thy perſon and care to the Commonwealth; for as thou ſhalt do right or wrong in this, ſo expect from God who will judge thee in this thing.</hi> The Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>Rome</hi> flouriſhed, were enjoined by an Oath, the ſubſtance thus: <hi>You ſhall ſwear by Jupiter Olympian, and Counſeller, and by Veſtal the Conſultreſs, and by Jupiter the Marrier, and Juno the Married, and Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va the Provident, and Victor, and Venus, and Amity, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and Right, and Equity, and good Fortune, and all other Gods and Goddeſſes, that I reſolve to ſpeak my opinion according to the Lawes and Ordinances approved by the City, according to the Decrees and Edicts of the Romans, by the which our Commonwealth is govern'd, having reſpect to the profit of my Country with all my power; I ſhal not ſuffer that my judgment or counſel ſhall be ſubject to favour, hatred, gifts or preſents; I ſhall not frame my Sentence to the will of any particular, nor join my ſelf to any man or party, but only to the common benefit, that I may to the utmoſt of my power increaſe the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> So that it appeareth, that the Commonwealth of <hi>Rome</hi> had a neceſſity to provide againſt partiallity, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of private intereſt: you ſhall not find one amongſt the Romans, during its glorious freedom (until corruptions gained footing in the Commonwealth) that was ever prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for being Cozen, Uncle, Father, Son, or otherwiſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but their tryals were their qualifications and abilities to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166475:12"/>undertake in peace or war for the good of the publick. In the forementioned Oath, you may mind one clauſe, which is, <hi>That they ſhall deliver their opinions according to the Laws and Ordinances approved by the City or Commonwealth;</hi> ſo that people that are free from being Lorded over by the claim of any one perſon as Monarch, are not bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obey any Laws but ſuch as they ſhall conſent to by a general approbation. <hi>Caius</hi> firſt directed his voice in his Orations to the people, and not minded the Senate; (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as other Orators that deceived the people, and flattered the Senate, directed their voice to the Senate) He reſtored the Authority of the people, and minded them that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was provided for their good, to deliver them from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the more powerful: and therefore it ſhould behove them to watch to their Liberty, that they ſhould not look upon any circumſtances in Religion to be qualifications for publick Truſts.</p>
            <p n="26">26. When a Government is contracted into the hands of one or more, that they come to pretend any thing of right to Government, that Commonwealth is ſeldome free from War, both Civil and Forraign: ſo that that bloud and treaſure that ſhould be ſpent in enlarging the Dominions of the Commonwealth, are ſpent in quarrels of ſuch perſons as lay claim to the Government: as an inſtance, the Wart between the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> wherein ſo much of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> bloud was ſpilt. That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhould be an inducement to caution <hi>England</hi> never to let any of their members grow too great, nor continue too long in great Truſts: <hi>Many claim a right by no other Title then long Continuance or Poſſeſſion.</hi> What miſerable Wars, Murders, Burnings, Depopulations, Cruelties of all kindes were committed in the times of <hi>Nero, Galba, Otho</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellius?</hi> which were perſonal quarrels of thoſe, to graſp at the Empire, and to hold it when poſſeſſed. Likewiſe the Civil War between <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> was the cauſe of he <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealths loſing of footing, by ſuffering two of their Members to grow to that greatneſſe, to be able to wage ſuch conſiderable Wars one againſt the other, by which means
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166475:12"/>the Victor became able to give a Law to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and could no longer reliſh receiving a Law from them, after he had taſted what large Command, and long continuance therein was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="27">27. If the Common-wealth hath many Warrs, they ſhould not put the Conduct on one Members ſhoulders; but rather chuſe ſeverall Members for ſeveral Undertakings; ſo that by this means there wil be ſeveral or many of equal credit, and therefore leſſe dangerous.</p>
            <p n="28">28. That thoſe that have the charge of the conduct of Armies, may not have the power of diſpoſing the Treaſurie, nor the levying thereof; but the Civil Power to act in that particular, that the Military power may know they are Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and not Maſters.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Care to increaſe Manufacture ought to be had, for that enricheth and civillizeth the people. Likewiſe care in Commerce, to poize the exchange with Forreigners, leſt they eat you out of the Principal.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Not onely to be careful to provide good Laws, but alſo to provide a due execution, and that penalties may be inflicted againſt thoſe Magiſtrates that are remiſs in the due executions of thoſe Laws and Conſtitutions as are provided for the conſervation and good of the Publick.</p>
            <p n="31">31. That private motions or making of friends to obtain any thing whatſoever, may not be allowed of under great penalties.</p>
            <p n="32">32. That all perſons in truſt ſhould be limited to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws, Cuſtoms and Uſages of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and not otherwiſe then to the preſerving of juſt and equall Freedom. It is not to be underſtood of iuſt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Freedom or common libertie, to be any other thing then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to diſtinguiſh and preſerve Proprietie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
